Guide to the Andover Newton Miscellaneous Personal Papers Collection
Yale University Divinity School Library
- Individuals M-Z, Series II
  - Smith, Samuel Francis
    - Poems (Box 144, Folder 7-11)
      The poems are arranged by title or first line. They are primarily in manuscript format, with some printed.
    - Poem fragments and manuscripts (Box 144, Folder 12-14)
    - Correspondence, 1847-1895 (Box 145, Folder 1)
    - Sermons and sermon notes, 1843-1851, no date (Box 145, Folder 2)
    - Materials from the testimonial to Smith held in Boston on April 3, 1895, including program, testimonial letters and poems (Box 145, Folder 3)
    - Newspaper clippings related to Smith (Box 145, Folder 4)
    - Materials related to "America" song (Box 145, Folder 5-7)
    - Memorabilia of Smith, including autograph book and "Last Will and Testament" (Box 145, Folder 8)
    - Family papers: correspondence, newspaper clippings, memorabilia, including 2 cookbooks of Mary White Smith, 1863-1914 (Box 145, Folder 9-11)
    - Materials related to Smith Homestead in Newton Centre, Massachusetts, including photographs, 1957-1967 (Box 145, Folder 12-13)
    - Photographs of Smith and family (Box 146, Folder 1-2)
    - Miscellaneous photographs (Box 146, Folder 3)
  - Smyth, Egbert Coffin
    Smyth was born August 24, 1829 in Brunswick, Maine. He graduated from Bowdoin College in 1848 and Bangor Theological Seminary in 1853. Ordained as a Congregational minister in 1856, he served at Bowdoin College as Professor of Rhetoric and Oratory 1854-1856, and Professor of Natural and Revealed Religion 1856-1862. Following study at Berlin and Halle Universities, Smyth was Professor of Ecclesiastical History at Andover Theological Seminary from 1863 to 1904 and Lecturer in Pastoral Theology 1863-1868. He was editor of the Andover Review from 1884-1893. Smyth died in Andover on April 12, 1904.
    - Lecture notes from time at Bangor Theological Seminary, including on Doctrinal Theology, Homiletics, and Rhetoric, 1851-1852 (Box 147, Folder 1-2)
    - Journal: primarily notes regarding sermons and revivals, 1857-1900 (Box 147, Folder 3)
    - Notebook recording subjects of themes, 1845-1893 (Box 147, Folder 4)
    - Notebook recording examinations and honorary scholarships essay topics, 1884-1903 (Box 147, Folder 5)
    - Lectures: Ancient Church, Atonement, Biblical History (Box 147, Folder 6-8, Box 148, Folder 1-12)
    - Lectures: Church Doctrine of the Son, Church History, The Creed, Doctrine of God (Box 149, Folder 1-11, Box 150, Folder 1-4)
    - Lectures: Doctrine of Sin, Ethics, Existence of God, External History of the Nicene (Box 150, Folder 5-9)
    - Lectures: Gospel of Peter, Inputation, Lessing and Kant, Medieval Church, Mysticism, Modern Christology, Old Catholic Church (Box 151, Folder 1-12)
    - Lectures: Principles of the Great Reformation, Soteriology, unlabeled (Box 152, Folder 1-3)
  - Stiles, Abel
    Stiles was born in Windsor, Connecticut in 1709. He graduated from Yale College in 1733 and served as a tutor there from 1736-1737. Ordained as a Congregational minister on July 23, 1737, Stiles served the First Congregational Church, Woodstock, Connecticut from 1737 to 1760 and the North Congregational Church in Woodstock from 1760 to 1783. He died on July 25, 1783 in Woodstock.
    - Sermons, 1740-1759, no date (Box 153, Folder 1-21)
      For a full listing of exact dates and scriptural texts for the sermons, see the inventory in Box 153 Folder 1.
  - Taylor, Oliver Alden
    Taylor was born in Yarmouth, Massachusetts on August 28, 1801. He attended Allegheny College 1821-1822 and graduated from Union College in 1825. He received a certificate from Andover Theological Seminary in 1829. Taylor was engaged in literary work in Andover from 1829 to 1838 and was an Instructor in Sacred Literature at Andover Theological Seminary from 1836 to 1837. He was ordained in 1838, preached in Greenfield, Massachusetts 1838-1839 and was minister of the Manchester Congregational Church in Massachustetts from 1839 until his death in 1851.
    - Student reading and sermon notes (Box 154, Folder 1-7)
    - Student addresses, 1828-1829 (Box 154, Folder 8)
    - Draft of preface to catalogue for Andover Theological Seminary library (Box 154, Folder 9)
    - Unpublished manuscript, "History of the Pulpit," (Box 154, Folder 10-13)
  - West, Stephen
    West was born on November 2, 1735 in Tolland, Connecticut. He graduated from Yale College in 1755. He was ordained on June 15, 1759, in Stockbridge, Massachusetts and was pastor of the First Congregational Church in Stockbridge from 1758 to 1818. He died on May 13, 1819.
    - Sermons: #64 - #325, 1759-1765 (Box 155, Folder 1-30)
      The sermons in this collection are arranged according to a numerical sequence assigned by West. Since the order is primarily chronological, unnumbered sermons are listed in appropriate chronological position. There is an index to the scriptural texts of the sermons in Box 155 Folder 1.
    - Sermons: #326 - #514, 1765-1768 (Box 156, Folder 1-24)
    - Sermons: #515 - #715, 1768-1772 (Box 157, Folder 1-33)
    - Sermons: #716 - #961, 1773-1781 (Box 158, Folder 1-41)
    - Sermons: #962 - #1175, 1781-1788 (Box 159, Folder 1-38)
    - Sermons: #1176 - #1464, 1788-1794 (Box 160, Folder 1-37)
    - Sermons: #1467 - #2440, 1794-1818, no date (Box 161, Folder 1-45)
  - White, William James
    While was born on March 11, 1811 in Tolland, Connecticut. He attended Brown University 1835-1837 and graduated from Williams College in 1839. He graduated from Andover Theological Seminary in 1842 and following his ordination served as a home missionary in Chateaugay, Canada from 1842 to 1843 and in Concord, Michigan in 1844. He served as pastor of churches in Lubec and Whiting, ME (1844-1846) and Fairfax and Fletcher, VT (1847-1847). From 1849 to 1889 he was a businessman in Worcester, MA, where he died on October 20, 1889.
    - Letters to his brother Charles, written while White was a student at Andover Theological Seminary, 1840-1842, no date (Box 162, Folder 1)
  - Whitman, Benaiah Longley
    Whitman was born on November 21, 1862 in Wilmot, Nova Scotia. He graduated from Brown University in 1887 and Newton Theological Institution in 1890. Ordained as a Baptist minister on September 13, 1887, he served churches in Newton Upper Falls (1887-1888) and Grafton, MA (1888-1889), and Portland, ME (1889-1892). Whitman was President of Colby College from 1892 to 1895 and of Columbian College in Washington, DC from 1895-1900. He then served Baptist churches in Philadelpha (1900-1907)and Seattle, WA (1907-1911), where he died on November 27, 1911.
    - Journal, 1907 March 21 - July 13 (Box 162, Folder 2)
      The journal relates Whitman's observations and experiences as he travelled from Philadelphia to Japan, China, Russia and into parts of Europe in 1907. This a photocopy; the original was retained by the donor, Robert S. Walker (1987).There is a microfilm copy of the journal.
  - Willard, Benjamin
    Benjamin Willard was born in Lancaster, MA. in 1783. He joined the Baptist Church in Harvard, MA in 1800 and was licensed to preach by that church in 1818. He conducted missionary tours in northern New England and Canada under the sponsorship of the Massachusetts Baptist Missionary Society 1818-1821. He began ministry in Northampton, MA in 1822 and was ordained in 1823. The Baptist Church in Northampton was formally organized in 1826. He continued as pastor of the Northampton Church until 1838. For several years thereafter he did evangelistic work among Vermont Baptist Churches. Willard died in Holyoke, MA December 2, 1862.
    - Correspondence, 1821-1834 (Box 162, Folder 3-6)
      Correspondents include Isaac Kimball, Luther Rice, Zeph.Swift Moore, Isaac Briggs, Jr., Francis Wayland, Jr., George D. Boardman, Thomas Rand. A complete listing of letters is available in Box 162, Folder 3.
  - Winchell, James Manning
    Winchell was born on September 8, 1791 in North East, New York. He attended Union College 1808-1811 and graduated from Brown University in 1812. He was licensed to preach by North East Baptist Church in 1812 and was minister at the Baptist Church in Bristol RI from 1812-1813. He was ordained in 1813 and was minister at the First Baptist Church, Boston, MA from 1814 to 1820, when he died.
    - 3 sermons, 1817, no date (Box 163, Folder 1)
    - Transcriptions of sermons by Winchell (2 bound volumes), No date (Box 163, Folder 2-3)
  - Wisner, Benjamin Blydenberg
    Wisner was born in 1794 in Goshen, New York. He graduated from Union College in 1813 and from Princeton Theological Seminary in 1818. He was ordained as a Congregational minister in 1821 and served Old South Church, Boston, MA from 1821 to 1832. Wisner was Secretary of the American Board of Commissioners for Foreign Missions from 1832 until his death in 1835.
    - Sermons, 1823-1830 (Box 164, Folder 1-26)
    - Sermons, 1830-1831 (Box 165, Folder 1-8)
    - Confession of faith, No date (Box 165, Folder 9)
  - Woods, Leonard (1774-1854)
    Woods graduated from Harvard in 1796 and was ordained as pastor of the Congregational Church in West Newbury, MA in 1798. He was a founder of of Andover Theological Seminary and served as Professor of Christian Theology there from 1808 to 1846, and as Professor Emeritus until his death in 1854.
    Related Materials
    The contents of a packet addressed to Edwards Amasa Park that was labeled "Leonard Woods' orations" have been placed with the Park papers in RG 291 because the authorship of manuscripts is unclear and one dates from after Woods' death.
    - Account book and correspondence related to portrait of Leonard Woods, 1848-1852 (Box 166, Folder 1)
  - Woods, Leonard (1807-1878)
    Woods, son of Andover Theological Seminary professor Leonard Woods, was born on November 24, 1807 in Newbury, Massachusetts. He graduated from Union College in 1827 and from Andover Theological Seminary in 1830. His translation of Georg Christian Knapp's Christian Theology (1831-1833) was long used as a textbook in American theological seminaries. After serving as professor of sacred literature at Bangor Theological Seminary for three years, Woods was president of Bowdoin College from 1839 to 1866. He died in Boston on December 24, 1878.
    - Manuscript sermons, including "Christian Contentment", "Spread of the Gospel", "Propagation of Christianity", 1839-1848 (Box 166, Folder 2-9)
      Sermons in Box 166 Folders 2-9 were found in a packet addressed to Edwards Amasa Park that was labeled "Leonard Woods' orations." It is assumed that the author was Leonard Woods, Jr. based on handwriting and dates.
    - Baccalaureate address, 1859 (Box 166, Folder 10)
      From packet addressed to Edwards Amasa Park labeled "Leonard Woods' orations"
    - Sermon: "State of Mind necessary for the perception of Religious Truth", No date (Box 166, Folder 11)
    - Miscellaneous notes and fragments, No date (Box 166, Folder 12-13)
    - Lecture notes, No date (Box 166, Folder 14-17)